Stop paying for expensive image
generation tools as there's a better
stable diffusion alternative that has a
more intuitive interface than ComfyUI
and Automatic111.
I'm talking about Fooocus, an advanced
image generator that lets you create
stunning, high-quality images from text
prompts with just a few clicks. Plus,
it's completely free. So, in this video,
we'll learn how to use Fooocus AI on
Google Colab, explore its features,
perform text-to-image and image-to-image
generation, adjust advanced settings,
and offer prompting tips. We'll also
evaluate its pros and cons.
Let's get started by clicking on the
Google Colab link that I have given in
the description below. Once the link is
loaded, you'll see this code. Click on
the run button to start running our
Fooocus file on Google Colab.
This might take some time, depending on
your internet speed. Mine took 10
minutes.
And here, we have finally reached the
main interface of our Fooocus Google
Colab.
Let's get started with Fooocus AI's
text-to-image feature. We'll first use
the default settings and then get into
the advanced ones to see the full range
of possibilities.
I'm going to enter a text prompt here, a
serene sunset over a neighborhood in a
mountain lake.
Now, let's click on the generate button
and see what happens.
Fooocus AI will take a moment to process
the prompt and generate the best
possible image. Once it's done, the
image will pop up on the screen.
This image seems good. The overall
quality, everything is to the point. The
sunset, the details, and everything else
seem natural and great. But I feel like
trying more styles, too.
Let's try a more specific prompt for
this. To make an AI tool work exactly
upon your words, there are some rules to
communicate with it.
When assigning a task to AI, use the act
as if strategy. For example,
Hi, Fuocus. I want you to act as if you
are an anime artist.
Now, be specific about the task, like
and draw a drone shot of a serene sunset
with orange haze lightly falling on the
three houses beside the mountain lake.
You can add up more details to it, like
do add up some people and crowd in the
drawing.
When you're done with the prompt, you
can tweak the styles and effects of your
image by clicking on the advanced
feature.
Fuocus has already selected some default
settings and styles, but it's completely
up to you to change them or stick with
the defaults.
Let's now set our preset, and according
to our prompt, I like this anime one
better.
Here, these are some options to choose
for performance, from which the quality
one uses 60 sampling steps to generate
the image.
The speed one uses 30 sampling steps,
while the extreme quality option
generates images of perfect quality
using LCM Laura.
I'm selecting speed one.
As you scroll down a bit, you'll see the
option to select the aspect ratio of
your image. I usually stick with the
default setting, which is 9 is to 7.
Next, you can choose how many images the
tool will generate for each prompt. I
like to set this to five images.
One of my favorite features of any AI
tool is the negative prompt.
After selecting your preferred image
format, you can type a prompt to exclude
specific elements you don't want.
For example, here I want none of the
houses should be made of wood.
After typing in, let's scroll back up.
Here, I'll select the styles for my
image.
It's great that they've included sample
images to show us what each feature can
do.
Since Fooocus supports Stable Diffusion
XL, you also have the option to choose a
refiner model if you're using SDXL
models.
From my experience with similar AI
tools, the recommended weight for Laura
models usually falls between 0.5 and
0.1.
However, each Laura might have its own
optimal strength, producing different
results based on that setting.
If the weight is set too low, the
influence of Laura might not be
noticeable.
On the other hand, setting it too high
can limit the model's flexibility and
lower the image quality.
So, I'll go with a safe bet and set it
at 0.5.
All right, next up are the advanced
settings.
This AI can take guidance up to a scale
of seven, which is pretty cool.
Since my prompt is a bit complex,
featuring a neighborhood, lake,
mountain, and sunset, I want the image
to be more lively. So, I'm setting the
image sharpness to 11.
Now, all that's left is to click
generate and see the results.
I love it when an AI tool really
responds to my input and guidance. It's
so satisfying when it turns out exactly
as I expected. Now, let's get into
image-to-image generation. First, let's
switch things up a bit. I'll upload our
picture here and ask Fooocus to make
some changes to it.
Now, I'll click on the describe option
and let the tool generate a prompt based
on the photo.
See, it has given us a prompt about what
it sees in this photo. This is a sunset
over a lake and mountains.
Now, I'll click on generate and here are
our results.
These images are quite similar to the
original, but didn't incorporate my
neighborhood details. Even so, I have to
say the accuracy is still pretty high.
Next, let me show you the image prompt
feature for image-to-image generation.
This feature allows you to create new
images based on the ones you provide.
As you can see on the screen, there are
four slots where you can upload images
for the tool to use as references.
Let's give it a try. I'll upload an
image of a celebrity in the first slot
and an image of a fantasy warrior in the
second slot.
Now, I'll click generate and let's see
the results.
Notice how it has combined both details
beautifully. The tool has taken
inspiration from the red carpet theme
from the celebrity image and the fantasy
elements from the warrior photo. It's
impressive how well it followed the
details from both images. You can easily
compare it with paid tools like
Midjourney.
Speaking of the installation process,
it's very quick and proceeds with a
single click. There are no premium
options. The tool is completely free and
can be used offline.
It's very beginner-friendly and easier
to use than Automatic1111
and ComfyUI.
However, the output quality of the
images largely depends on the models
used. Fooocus also can sometimes be
sluggish depending on the intricacy of
your prompt and the effects you choose.
When running it on Google Colab, like
any online application, even a minor
internet issue can cause it to crash,
requiring you to reload the Python code
to get a working link again.
Google Colab also has usage
restrictions, so after generating a few
images, the tool might stop working.
But overall, Fooocus AI is a free and
easy to use stable diffusion model that
you can use to tell stories and make ads
without paying a dime.
And if you want an even better tool to
create consistent characters for free,
check out this video next.